Preliminary Inventory of the William D. Moreland Papers, 1949-1965
Hoover Institution Archives
William D. Moreland Papers,
1949-1965
59002
Moreland, William D.
5 manuscript boxes, 8 envelopes (2.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, reports, dispatches, newspapers, clippings, other printed matter, and photographs, relating to political, economic, and social conditions in West Africa.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
United States. Consulate (Dakar, Senegal); United States. Dept. of State.; Africa.; Africa, West.; Africa, West--Economic conditions.; Africa, West--Politics and government.; Africa, West--Social conditions.; Senegal.; Senegal--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations.; United States--Foreign relations--Senegal.; Diplomats--United States.
Container List
- General Africa
  - French West Africa (Box 1, Folder 1.1)
  - Dakar (Folder 1.1.A)
  - Senegal (Folder 1.2)
  - Mauritania (Folder 1.3)
  - French Guinea (Folder 1.4)
  - Ivory Coast (Folder 1.5)
  - Dahomey (Box 2, Folder 1.6)
  - French Niger (Folder 1.7)
  - Upper Volta (Folder 1.8)
  - French Sudan (Folder 1.9)
  - Sudan (Folder 1.9.A)
  - Togo (Folder 1.10)
- Economic
  - French West Africa (Folder 2.1)
  - Ports (Folder 2.2)
  - Railroads (Folder 2.3)
  - Roads (Folder 2.4)
  - Aviation (Folder 2.5)
  - Agriculture (Folder 2.6)
  - Agricultural societies (Folder 2.6.A)
  - Name crops (Folder 2.6.B)
  - Animals; fish (Folder 2.6.C)
  - Forests (Folder 2.6.D)
  - Mining (Folder 2.7)
  - Industry (Folder 2.8)
  - Research (Folder 2.9)
  - Marshall Plan (Folder 2.10)
  - PERDES FIDES (Folder 2.11)
- Social
  - General (Box 3, Folder 3.1)
  - Education (Folder 3.2)
  - Health and sanitation (Folder 3.3)
  - Nutrition (Folder 3.3.A)
  - Labor (Folder 3.4)
  - Housing; urbanization (Folder 3.5)
  - Folklore; religion; handicraft (Folder 3.6)
  - Religion, Christian (Folder 3.7)
- Political
  - FWA (Folder 4.1)
  - Parties (Folder 4.2)
  - RDA (Folder 4.2.A)
- Natural Resources
  - Water (Folder 5.1)
  - Soil (Folder 5.2)
- Other Africa
  - French Equatorial Africa (Folder 6.1)
  - British West Africa (Folder 6.2)
  - Liberia (Folder 6.3)
  - Belgian Africa (Folder 6.4)
- Colonial policy
  - History (Folder 7.2)
  - Technical assistance (including American) (Folder 7.3)
- Geography
  - Geographic Service (Folder 8.1)
  - Maps (Folder 8.2)
  - Photographs (Folder 8.3)
- French politics (Folder 10)
- Bibliography and names (Folder 11)
- "Survey of the Operations of Marshall Plan Aid in French West Africa," by Consul William D. Moreland and Miss Virginia Robinson, Geographic Attaché, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- "The Political Situation of French West Africa," by William D. Moreland (Folder 2)
- Dispatches and reports on African conditions, 1950 (Folder 3)
- "Road Report on French West Africa and Togo," 1951 (Folder 4)
- Miscellaneous memoranda, mostly written while assigned to TCA (original Point Four program), 1952-1954, and translations (some in 1950-1951 in Dakar) (Folder 5)
- Papers produced while with Intelligence Research State Department in Washington, 1951 September to 1952 February (?) (Folder 6)
- Republic of Niger (information and documents, put out by its U.N. delegation), No.1 (n.d.) (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Clippings on Africa, 1964-1965 (Folder 2)
- Dispatches from Dakar, 1950 (photocopies) (Folder 3)
- Correspondence, etc. regarding "Africa Project" (Ford Foundation) (Folder 4)
- Miscellaneous clippings on Africa (Folder 5)
- Miscellaneous material: speech, Information A.O.F., etc. (Folder 6)
- Dispatch on Aruba's "Royal Visit" in 1955 (photocopy) (Folder 7)
- Photographs (Othertype Photo file)
  - Dahomey: Pictures taken in or near Abomey, 1949 July 13 10:00 a.m. (taken by William D. Moreland)
  - Gold Coast: 1949, "Port" of Accra. Activity
  - Nigeria: Kano, 1949
  - French Guinea
    - Port of Conakry, 1949 May 21 3:00 p.m. (taken by William D. Moreland), 1
    - Main road, few miles south of Labe, 1949 May 25 noon (taken by William D. Moreland), 3
    - Native chieftains of village Boullivel, 12 miles north of Tolo. Foula race (taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 May 25 10:00 a.m.), 4
    - Details of bridge on road just north of Tolo. Horizontal logs are of wood impervious to insects and decay. This type of bridge designed and constructed by the administration of Cercle of Mamou (taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 May 25 10:00 a.m.), 5
    - Agricultural school at Tolo near Mamou. Assistant Administrator Delaroche at right (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 May 25 9:30 a.m.), 6
    - Ferry landing of Kolente River at Medina-Oula (taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 May 24 11:00 a.m.), 7
    - Ferry over Kolente River at Medina-Oula. Going Northeast (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 May 24 11:00 a.m.), 8
    - House of Lois Dupuy, Medina-Oula. From left to right: Mr. Dupuy, Miss Robinson, Mr. Louis Pezon, prominent Guinea planter and industrialist, and village Chief (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 May 24 11:30 a.m.), 9
    - Road between Medina-Oula and rice project north of town (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 May 24 noon), 10
    - Tractor plowing dry lake bed for rice cultivation. About 10 miles north of Medina-Oula (taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 May 24 noon), 11
    - Native dwelling in Medina-Oula (taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 May 24 2:00 p.m.), 12
    - Detail of pineapple and citrus plantation at La Kolente. Mr. Pezon, owner, in center (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 May 24 3:00 p.m.), 13
    - Main road from Kindia to Mamou at point where branch turns north to La Kolente (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 May 24 2:30 p.m.), 14
    - Main road in vicinity of KanKan near agricultural Station (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 May 27 3:00 p.m.), 15
    - Bridge over Milo River at KanKan. Looking Southwest. Temporary bridge showing in one picture removed in 1950 March. Also 2 small bridges in dike or causeway at the Eastern approach to bridge (taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 May 28 2:30 p.m.), 16
    - Road between KanKan and Kerouane (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 May 28 4:00 p.m.), 17
    - Kitchen and boys at native run restaurant and rest house at Kerouane (pictures taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 May 28 4:30 p.m.), 18
    - Macenta (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 May 29 9:00 a.m.), 19
    - Left to right: Mrs. Hamel, Assistant Administrator S. Hamel, Miss V. Robinson. Macenta (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 May 29 10:00 a.m.), 20
    - Sample bridge on main road between Macenta and Seredou (pictures taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 May 30 9:00 a.m.), 21
    - Quinine plantation 14 kilometers South of Seredou, about 3,000 feet altitude (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 May 30 11:00 a.m.), 22
    - Road between Macenta and Diani River on way to Nzerekore (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 May 30 4:00 p.m.), 23
    - Ferry over Diani River on main road between Macenta and Nzerekore (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 May 30 4:30 p.m.), 24
    - Bridge of vines across Diani River on road between Macenta and Nzerekore. Crossing also served by hand propelled ferry capacity one 5 ton truck (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 May 30 4:30 p.m.), 25
    - Custom stop at Dieke before crossing ferry on Mani River into Liberia (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 May 31 11:30 a.m.), 26
    - Delauney house, 1949, 27
    - Dalaba, 1949, 28
    - Liberia Border, 1949, 29
    - Kindia market, 1949. Pasteur Institute Research on tropical Parasites, 30
  - Ivory Coast
    - Logging near Agboville (pictures taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 June 15 4:00 p.m.), 1
    - Sample small bridge on main road about half way between Agboville and Abengourou (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 June 16 10:00 a.m.), 2
    - Secondary road in Banco forest near Abidjan (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 June 11 11:00 a.m.), 3
    - Bar across canal from sea to lagoon at Abidjan. Bar will be removed in summer 1950 (picture taken from Dutch dredge "Maitena" by William D. Moreland, 1949 June 10 9:00 a.m.), 4
    - Seaward end of canal for port of Abidjan. Temporary landing system utilizing U.S. landing craft, which go to ships anchored in open sea (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 June 10 9:00 a.m.), 5
    - Canal de Vridi, Abidjan, looking seaward on East bank. Temporary loading and facilities for sacked products at sea end of unfinished canal. Ex-U.S. landing craft transport to ships anchored in sea, 1949 May (picture taken by William D. Moreland), 6
    - Same, 7
    - Cocoa inspection and houses near Agboville, 1949, 8
  - Togo
    - School building at Amegneran is typical of two to four class school building throughout coastal and savanna areas in French West Africa (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 July 2 12:00 noon), 1
    - Secondary road about 10 miles North of Lama Kara. At time of picture, 1949 July, this road was not connected with any other road although it traversed heavily populated areas (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 July 6 12:00 noon), 2
    - Representative natives on unfinished road 10 miles North of Lama Kara (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 July 6 12:00 noon), 3
    - View from edge of unfinished road in mountain, 10 miles North of Lama Kara (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 July 6 12:00 noon), 4
    - Type of native dwellings in heavily populated areas in hills north of Lama Kara (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 July 6 12:00 noon), 5
    - Main road between Sokode and Lama Kara about 15 miles south of Lama Kara (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 July 6 12:00 noon), 6
    - Defile on road between Sokode and Lama Kara, almost exactly half way between two cities (pictures taken from North looking South by William D. Moreland, 1949 July 5 5:00 p.m.), 7
    - Ferry crossing on road between Lome, Togo, and Cotonou, Dahomey at Grand Popo, Dahomey (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 July 10 11:30 a.m.), 8
    - Berard family and miscellany, 1949, 9
  - Niger
    - Aerial view of Kano and small village north of Kano, Nigeria (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 July 28 10:00 a.m.), 1
    - Heavy machinery graveyard at Zinder (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 July 28 5:30 p.m.), 2
    - Main road to Agades and North Africa 5 miles north of Zinder. Car in picture headed North (pictures taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 July 29 5:30 p.m.), 3
    - Market place scenes at Myrriah, an oasis 15 miles east of Zinder which supplies water for Zinder (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 July 31 10:00 a.m.), 4
    - Military review at Zinder (pictures taken from in front of Fort by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 3 7:30 a.m.), 5
    - Air France, Custom, police and airport offices at Zinder (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 4 11:30 a.m.), 6
    - Governor's place at Niamey, capital of Niger, facing Niger River and view of river from steps (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 5 5:00 p.m.), 7
    - Government's guest house at Niamey, near Government offices and residences (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 6 5:00 p.m.), 8
  - Sudan (now Mali)
    - Niger River at Ansongo looking westward. Protuberances believed to be pre-historic ruins such as found in Tigris Valley (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 9 3:00 p.m.), 1
    - Market place at Ansongo (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 9 3:00 p.m.), 2
    - Grain storage jars at Ansongo (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 9 3:00 p.m.), 3
    - Road at northern edge of Ansongo going to Gao (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 9 3:45 p.m.), 4
    - Road between Ansongo and Gao approximately 25 miles South East of Gao (pictures taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 9 5:30 p.m.), 5
    - Native Bella women at well, outskirts of Gao (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 10 10:00 a.m.), 6
    - Road between Gao and Bourem close to Gao. Looking North (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 11 8:00 a.m.), 7
    - Road between Gao and Bourem about midway (pictures taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 11 8:30 a.m.), 8
    - "Gardes de Cercle" at Bourem (pictures taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 11 10:00 a.m.), 9
    - Entrance to fort at Bourem (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 11 3:30 p.m.), 10
    - Interior of Fort at Bourem (pictures taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 11 3:30 p.m.), 11
    - Residence of "Commandant de Cercle" ta Bourem (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 11 3:00 p.m.), 12
    - Water system at Bourem. Barrels rolled into Niger River, filled and rolled back to town (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 11 3:00 p.m.), 13
    - Soft sand road between Bourem and Gao, 8 miles south of Bourem (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 11 5:00 p.m.), 14
    - Road on outskirts of Kokry on Niger River leading towards colonization village of Nara, West of Kokry (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 26 2:00 p.m.), 15
    - Colonization village of Bamako (not Bamako the capital) on the outskirts of Kokry on Niger River (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 26 2:00 p.m.), 16
    - Main road between Kokry and Macina on north bank of Niger River. M. Pavillon, Ingenieur Office du Niger, on the picture (taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 26 5:00 p.m.), 17
    - Natives at boat landing at Diafarabe (pictures taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 27), 18
    - Niger River. Typical village on Niger River just North of Mopti (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 30), 19
    - On Board Niger River steamer S. S "Marechal Galieni" at time of running aground on Lake Debo. East end (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 29 5:00 p.m.), 20
    - Niger River. Niafounke. New market place to left (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 30), 21
    - Niger River. Timbuktu. Believed to be the only sign in existence with name of town "Tombouctou" approximately 2 miles South of town on road to river port (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 31 8:00 a.m.), 22
    - Niger River. Ancient mosque at Timbuktu (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 31 10:00 a.m.), 23
    - Niger River. Building at eastern outskirts of Timbuktu (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1950 August 31 10:00 a.m.), 24
    - Niger River. Views in center of Timbuktu (pictures taken by William Morealand, 1949 August 31 10:00 a.m.), 25
    - Niger River. Market place at Timbuktu (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 31 11:00 a.m.), 26
    - Two types of main road between Timbuktu and Goundam, about midway, 1949 August 31 3:30 p.m.), 27
    - Niger River. General view of Goundam looking North from top of Mosque (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 31 5:30 p.m.), 28
    - Niger River. Goundam. View from top of Mosque Eastward, residence of Commandant de Cercle in distance (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 31 5:30 p.m.), 29
    - Mosque at Goundam (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 31 5:30 p.m.), 30
    - Niger River. Natives at ship landing, Niafounke (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 September 1 1:00 p.m.), 31
    - Niger River. Tug and barges crossing Lake Debo (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 September 1), 32
    - Niger River, SS Marechal Galieni at berth, Mopti (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 September 1 10:00 a.m.), 33
    - Burial tombs and storerooms in cliffs of the "Falaises of Sangha" (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 September 4 9:30 a.m.), 34
    - Sangha. View of plain South East from midway of cliffs of Sangha (pictures taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 September 4 9:30 a.m.), 35
    - Sangha. Cliffs, looking almost straight up (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 September 4 10:00 a.m.), 36
    - Sangha. Vegetation and debris at base of cliffs (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 September 4 10:00 a.m.), 37
    - Sangha. Typical native villages at base of "Falaise de Sangha" just below town of Sangha (pictures taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 September 4 11:00 a.m.), 38
    - Mosque at Sofara. Largest building in the town and typical of the region (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 September 6 10:00 a.m.), 39
    - Main road between Mopti and San, about half way (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 September 6 10:00 a.m.), 40
    - Ferry across Niger River at Bamako, loading on South West side of river (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 September 8 5:30 p.m.), 41
    - Timbuktu, 42
    - Bamako. Air pictures, 1949 and 1950, 43
  - Upper Volta
    - Moro Naba, Emperor of the Mossis in center. Governor Mouragues to his right, Miss Robinson and Madame Mourages to his left. Ouagadougou (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 13 5:30 p.m.), 1
    - Bridge near Bobo Dioulasso. Defective original design caused wash out of approaches (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 15 5:30 p.m.), 2
  - Senegal
    - Faidherbe bridge at St. Louis from East, or mainland end (taken by Jocelyn K. Moreland, 1950 August 6), 24
    - St. Louis. Main bridge from island to coastal strip. See 29 for monument at far end. Trees are on Island side (taken by Jocelyn K. Moreland, 1950 August), 28
    - St. Louis, Senegal Monument to War Dead at western end of main bridge joining Island with coastal strip (taken by Jocelyn K. Moreland, 1950 August), 29
    - St. Louis. Senegal, Gendarme Post on coastal strip near Mauritania Government offices (taken by Jocelyn K. Moreland, 1950 August), 30
    - St. Louis. Representative buildings and streets just south of Governor's palace, on island (taken by Jocelyn K. Moreland, 1950 August), 33
    - St. Louis. Police headquarters north of Governor's palace on island (taken by Jocelyn K. Moreland, 1950 August), 35
    - St. Louis, City Hall. Streets too narrow to permit more perspective (taken by Jocelyn K. Moreland, 1950 August, 36
    - St. Louis. Quai-side on east branch of river - east side of island (taken by Jocelyn K. Moreland, 1950 August), 37
    - St. Louis. Littoral, 1950 August, 38
  - Mauritania
    - To Boutilimit from St. Louis, 1951 May, 1
    - Aleg to Senegal, 1951 May, 2
- Amendments to inventory of photographs
  - Sudan
    - Sudan - Niger River. Natives at boat landing at Diafarabé. Diafarabé is the angle of Mot de Diaka and Niger River on north bank Niger between Segou and Mopti (taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 August 27), 18
    - Bamako. Air Pix, 1949 and 1950. Airplane in pre-WW II junkers - then Fr. Air Force - we rode it to Dakar from Bamako in 1949, 43
  - Dahomey
    - Probably at Abomey, 1949, 1a
    - Native metal workers at Abomey (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 July 13 10:00 a.m.), 1b
  - French Guinea
    - House of Louis Dupuy, the only motor vehicle tractor mechanic for miles around, Médina-Oula. Left to right: Mr. Dupuy, Miss Robinson, Mr. Louis Pezon, prominent Guinea planter and industrialist, and village Chief (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 May 24 11:30 a.m.), 9
    - Road between Macenta and Diani River on way to Nzerekore. "Sacred Forest". Great difficulty getting a driver for this trip. Full of evil spirits (picture taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 May 30 4:00 p.m.), 23
    - Delauney House. Inside banana and pineapple planter's house near Kindia, 1949, 27
    - Liberia Border. The truck we rode for 12 hours. N'zerekore to Firestone plantation, 1949, 29
  - Ivory Coast
    - Canal de Vridi, Abidjan, looking seaward on east bank. Temporary loading facilities for sacked products at sea end of unfinished canal. Ex-U.S. landing craft transport to ships anchored in sea (taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 May), 6
    - Canal de Vridi, Abidjan looking westward. Dutch dredge, "Maitena" and other vessels in seaward end of unfinished canal (taken by William D. Moreland, 1949 May), 7
  - Togo
    - Berard Family - Commandant de Cercle, Amecho; market-mid Togo; landscape-mid Togo, 1949, 9